<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fxecution [sic] of the late King, justified; and the Parliament and army therein vindicated: published for satisfaction to the kingdome, by a wel-wisher to the safety and freedom thereof.</title>
            <author>Wel-wisher to the safety and freedom.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84285</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3855</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E545_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201964</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862437</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862437</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114596</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84285)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114596)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E545[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fxecution [sic] of the late King, justified; and the Parliament and army therein vindicated: published for satisfaction to the kingdome, by a wel-wisher to the safety and freedom thereof.</title>
                  <author>Wel-wisher to the safety and freedom.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 11, 20-26, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Simmons, in Aldersgate Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb 26 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114596:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Execution of the late KING, JUSTIFIED; And the Parliament and Army therein VINDICATED: Publiſhed for Satisfaction to the Kingdome,</p>
            <p>By a Wel-wiſher to the ſafety and freedom thereof.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Deut. 16.18.</hi>
                  </bibl> Judges and Officers ſhalt thou make thee in all the Cities which the Lord thy God giveth thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Deut. 1.17.</hi>
                  </bibl> Yee ſhall have no reſpect of perſon in judgement, ye ſhall not feare the face of man, for the judgement is Gods.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Amos 5.24.</hi>
                  </bibl> And let judgement run downe as waters, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe as a mighty River.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jer. 22.17.</hi>
                  </bibl> But thy eyes and thy heart are but onely for thy covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to ſhed innocent blood, and for oppreſſion and deſtruction even to doe this.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Levit. 23.17.</hi>
                  </bibl> He that killeth any man, ſhall be put to death.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Numb. 35.31, 33.</hi>
                  </bibl> Moreover yee ſhall take no recompence for the life of the murtherer, which is worthy to dye: but hee ſhall be put to death. So yee ſhall not pollute the Land wherein yee ſhall dwell: for blood defileth the Land, and the Land cannot be cleanſed of the blood that is ſhed therein, but by the blood of him that ſhed it.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jer. 22.18.</hi>
                  </bibl> Therefore, thus ſaith the Lord, againſt <hi>Jehoiakim,</hi> the Son of <hi>Joſiah</hi> King of Judah, they ſhall not lament him, ſaying: Ah, my Brother, or ah Siſter, neither ſhall they mourne for him, ſaying, Ah, Lord, or ah, his glory.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Simmons,</hi> in Alderſgate Street, 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114596:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114596:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Judicious Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Thought good (in times of ſo great and voluntary diſtraction and diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction about our civil rights) to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie my integrity to the good of this my native Countrey, according to my ability by ſome following Propoſitions and reſolutions of doubts thereupon in reference to the late tranſactions of Parliament and Army in juſtice upon the late King, and the rather (though many more rationall and ſo ſhould have been more ſatisfactory diſcourſes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon hath been publiſhed) becauſe ſome men notwithſtanding remaine obſtinate and perverſe under a cleere light; therefore as by many witneſſes
<pb facs="tcp:114596:3"/> a truth is the more confirmed, ſo by the multiplicity, diverſity, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of arguments and reaſons (as for ought I know theſe are from other mens) a juſt cauſe may be more cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſted, and the ſpirits of theſe men (being ſatisfied) reduced to an acknowledgement of the paſt equall proceedings of (though the minor part) the Parliament and Army, and the preſent perſeverance of both, in them, therefore when thou readeſt it, doe it not obſtinately, but be willing to bee convicted by the truth, which is the maine end for which I offer up theſe my firſt Fruits to thee and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which to attaine is the onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of him, who is thine unknowne friend in the peoples ſervice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114596:3"/>
            <head>THE Execution of the late KING, JUSTIFIED; And the Parliament and Army therein VINDICATED.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S wiſe Men before they build, lay a good foundation; ſo for a right proceſſion in this diſcourſe, wee muſt conſider the conſtitution of Government from which [not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rightly weighed] ſprings all our differences and contradictions in this Kingdome; I ſhall therefore ſtate the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Government two wayes, <hi>viz.</hi> Legall, and Illegal conſtitutions or ordination of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to explaine the tearmes; Lawfull ordination of Government is that which [as near as poſſible] is according to Gods preſcription: Unlawfull, is that which is contrary to, or diverſe from Gods preſcription in that way of Government which the people ſhall chooſe, which hath beene [according to the then immoderate importunity of the people] ſince <hi>Saul,</hi> almoſt hitherto, Kingly Government,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114596:4"/> and that in three lawfull reſpects, <hi>viz.</hi> By unction, the peoples approbation or election, and lawfull ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; ſo that whoſoever is qualified with theſe three particulars muſt be [according to the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of that Government] a lawfull King, but it being cleare that the firſt of theſe particulars [<hi>viz.</hi> immediate unction or unction by commandement] is withdrawne [ſo that in that ſenſe no King now can be called the Lords Anoynted] from us; it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, that he that is King by the peoples election or approbation, and lawfull ſucceſſion, is [according to the inſtitution of that Government] a warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted King: But on the contrary, he that is not ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected [lawfull ſucceſſion (to one freely choſen and not that uſurpt authority and forced ſubmiſſion) being onely beneficiall to a man for preferment in choyce, if he (as well qualified) come in compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition with others] his authority is uſurped and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legall. For let him plead ſucceſſion [though lawful] never ſo much, yet if the people forbeare to chooſe him, becauſe defective in his qualifications; hee is, in a degree as incapable as a Foole for the Office; ſo then lawfull ſucceſſion depending upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples election; hence will ariſe this undenyable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that that man that aſſumes the Kingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice onely by vertue of [though lawfull] ſucceſſion is a Uſurper, and doth preſume upon the peoples rights; now this was the onely plea that our late King had or could have to his Office: ſeeing he could pretend no right to it from unction, becauſe as (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid) it is withdrawne, neither from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple [it is cleare in that they have made so much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition againſt him] that hee continued in it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it from the peoples free election, that hee
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114596:4"/> reigned ſo long, in that he never acknowledged ſuch a power to be in them, 'twas onely then through an ignorant ſubmiſſion by them (or if they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of their right yet through their impotency) that our late King firſt aſſumed and ſince ſo long continued in the Office, now therefore, the title that he (on his part) claimed to it, and thereupon entred, was by a pretended right through [though illegall, becauſe originally from conqueſt] ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion: So that the premiſes conſidered, there needs no other proofe to demonſtrate that his title was uſurpt; yet for further conviction [and not to lay any more burthen upon him, or prejudice him in the thoughts of people, he having enough alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy where ever he be] and ſatisfaction to mens ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits concerning his Execution, and that wee may with more eaſe and contentedneſſe of minde (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the fleſh) forget him from whom wee had received, and could expect ſo little good [though his impenitency ſhould better us] let us conſider and review in our ſelves, his actions ſince his reigne, even to his very death (which ſhould ſadden us to thinke of) and they have cleerly demonſtrated that hee took it upon no other tearmes, then to rule ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will; which [though it lay in his heart from his firſt poſſeſſion] was not evaporated till theſe his latter and laſt yeares, wherein [the people claiming their rights] he hath moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly and audaciouſly [though contrary to all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon] declared himſelfe inaccountable to men, [though from them as a people (and ſo his Maſter) he had received, if it were Legall, his power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority] for his actions; then which nothing can more nullifie and fruſtrate the Law of God, which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114596:5"/> upon a breath thereof, doth include all whatſoever, without exception of perſons, under the penalty of it; as to inſtance ſeverall, univerſall injunctions of God in Scripture, <hi>Sine aliqua exceptione &amp; quae ad univerſos pertinent,</hi> without any exception, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to all alike as men: as in particular, that in <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.2. The Lord there ſpeaking unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſay alſo to the Children of Iſrael, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he be of the Children of Iſrael, or of the ſtrangers that dwell in Iſrael, that giveth his Children to Molech, he ſhall dye the death, &amp;c. Moſes</hi> and all the head Officers of the people being included in [if in this tranſgreſſion] the puniſhment thereof, in as much as they were among the Children of Iſrael; and in the 10. <hi>verſe</hi> of the ſame Chapter, God ſaith, <hi>The man that committeth adultery with another mans Wife, &amp;c. ſhall dye the death:</hi> Now we know, that the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of any, though never ſo high, doth not, or at leaſt ſhould not elevate him above his being, he is a man ſtill, though in Office a King, and though in reſpect thereof, God ſaith, <hi>I ſaid yee are Gods,</hi> that is in reſpect of your Office, be it high or low, which is, to manage your power in the execution of juſtice and judgement, in which you beare my image, yee are gods in being like God, though I have ſaid ſo, yet yee ſhall dye like men, which in the generall ſenſe of it, may have reſpect to a temporall death common to all men, whoſe nature you Magiſtrates beare, yet may very well beare this interpretation likewiſe, <hi>Yee ſhall dye like men;</hi> That is, all ſorts of men [if alike qualified] if murtherers, ye ſhall dye like men; that is, thoſe men that are murtherers; if adulterers, yee ſhall ſuffer like adulterers, the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor (in reference to many ſinnes) not the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114596:5"/> of the Law being taken away by Chriſt: Now then, the former interpretation agreeing with the precited Text, ſhewes clearly that the Law of God exempts none (neither high or low, rich or poore Magiſtrates or Subjects) from the puniſhment [in caſe of tranſgreſſion] thereof; now for any man to plead freedom [becauſe in the higheſt authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty] which notwithſtanding is derived, is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the Word of God, which ſaith, <hi>Numb.</hi> 35.30. <hi>Whoſoever killeth any perſon, the Judge ſhall ſlay the murtherer through witneſſes, &amp;c.</hi> And yet ſuch (would bee outlawes) will plead exemption; (I ſpeake not (onely in reference to this opinion in the late King) but to ſuch that are of his ſpirit, that connived at, and ſtill approve of ſuch an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in him, at leaſt at the impunity of it, whether they be Magiſtrates or others, yee looke more at the priviledge and the honour then the care of the Office, and therefore he was, and you are, far from <hi>Solomons</hi> ſpirit, that diſcerned it to bee the hardeſt matter to governe the people in righteouſneſſe, and therefore made it his prayer to God, to begge wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and that not for his owne ends, but to rule the people in equity; he made their good the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his endeavours, you, the late Kings preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, his riches, greatneſſe, and long life, the centers of yours; <hi>Solomon</hi> rejected all theſe, in competition with the peoples good, and how acceptable it was to God, will appeare in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.11. An example we have of the ſame ſpirit in Chriſt himſelfe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the good of his Sheep, <hi>John</hi> 10.11. Where he ſaith, <hi>I am that good Shepheard, that good Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard layeth downe his life for his Sheepe:</hi> But how diſtant was the ſpirit of the late King from ſuch a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114596:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114596:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:114596:7"/> temper, that for a little ſelfe accommodation and forcible preſervation of a few uſurpt Priviledges, to himſelfe, ſought to deſtroy (if hee were as Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard) his Sheep. The ſame example wee have of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 5.14. that would not burthen the people to pleaſure himſelfe: By this therefore it is evident that Kings have ſome earthly power above them, which they ſerve, and whoſe good muſt bee the end of their power; to which then, as their ſuperiour, they muſt be accountable, without which their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is uſurpt, and by which they are depoſed, preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or puniſhed, according to the demerit of their fault; Now then to confirme this, there is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Solomon,</hi> who was ſo farre from pleading any title of his owne to the Office, that in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of his prayer; he ſaith, <hi>Lord thou haſt made thy ſervant King</hi> (ſpeaking of himſelfe) <hi>in ſtead of David my Father;</hi> now that it is a righteous act up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on juſt grounds to prevent a ſucceſſor, it is manifeſt by this Gods owne example, becauſe that <hi>Adoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> by right of ſucceſſion, was heyre to the Crowne, yet notwithſtanding was prevented by God, who foreſaw, that the peoples good would not bee ſo much aimed at by him as by <hi>Solomon:</hi> So that here will ſitly intervene this obſervation, that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of all Magiſtrates depends upon their good behaviour, and that it is lawfull in caſe of miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour either to prevent or diſpoſeſſe them of their power. The proofe whereof, I ſhall further amplifie, in diſcuſſing particularly the kingly Office in the quality of it what it is, which I ſhall briefly reſolve in two particulers.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is a truſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, An Office or Duty.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:114596:7"/>
            <p>A truſt in that it is committed (not from God by injunction by which onely truſt is impoſed but by his permiſſion) to a man, from men; ſo then it cannot bee from ſucceſſion, which if lawfull, hath onely (in caſe of good behaviour) a preference to the truſt; that is, a man lawfully ſucceeding (if as well qualified as others) is to be prefer'd (in choice to the truſt) before them; therefore, as it is a truſt, ſo ſecondly it is a duty, in that hee is injoyned to performe that truſt, as by God that would have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man (like himſelfe) faithfull, ſo by men from whom hee receives his charge, and therefore they muſt needs be his intruſters, in that likewiſe the end of his truſt is for their owne good and welfare, to whom then he muſt without queſtion be accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and therefore a King to a people, is as an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countant to a Company, a Caſh-keeper to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: Now if a King, or any other Magiſtrate ſhall act quite contrary to the end of their truſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the peoples good, which was the conditions of their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and in ſtead thereof, make it as a mantle that thereunder they may more ſecurely preadvance their owne private intereſt, though directly preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall to the end of their Office; let the meaneſt capacity judge, whether ſuch a Magiſtrate or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates have not forfeited their truſt, upon which the intruſters may juſtly ceaſe, as to render to the perſon or perſons ſo offending according to his or their deſerts therein, ſo to inſtitute that truſt, that way the ſee beſt to diſcharge it, ſeeing the end thereof is their owne welfare; it is reaſon it ſelfe therefore, that the Servant ſhould bee accountable to his Maſter (for how ridiculous would it be for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Servant (a King being ſo to a people) becauſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114596:8"/> long intruſted without examination, to refuſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting, when by his Maſter called thereunto) wherein if defective he may juſtly exclude him his ſervice, for otherwiſe ſuch a ſervant would bee an intollerable burthen (and ſo fruſtrate the deſigne and end of ſervice which is for good and eaſe) to his Maſter, and therefore the reaſon why God (when he commanded the people to chooſe themſelves a King from among their brethren, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. from the 15. to the laſt verſe) preſcribed him Lawes and rules to walke by, and many things was forbidden him that hee might not be exalted above his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: And therefore <hi>Samuel</hi> 2.5.1. the Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> made this among others as an argument to them to make <hi>David</hi> their King, in that they were his bones and his fleſh: Now I need not make any application of this to the late King, ſince it is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely knowne how much he was (and in his ſeven yeares contention ſought to have been) exalted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove (not his brethren, becauſe not choſen from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them) the people; but it being before clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrated that he is guilty of breach of truſt herein, I need not appeale to rationall men of the juſtneſſe of the Parliaments and Armies late pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding againſt him, or make any further proofe of that his and his complices wilfull errour for an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power in him; yet for full and cleare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, I ſhall demonſtrate another proofe of the unlawfulneſſe and perniciouſneſſe of ſuch an inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable power in any Magiſtrates, and then cleare objections and conclude.</p>
            <p>The Propoſition was this, That the authority of Magiſtrates depends upon their good behaviour; I ſhall turne it into the negative, and from thence
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114596:8"/> prove it: ſo then if the authority of Magiſtrates, ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour as well as inferiour, depends not upon their good behaviour, then their power is abſolute, and they may doe what they will without contradiction or queſtioning, which is incroachment upon, and directly oppugnant to the rights and liberties of the people, and therefore ſuch a power is unlawfull. For firſt, it is againſt the Covenant that Magiſtrates take when they are firſt inveſted with power; which ſignifies that there is ſome bond or tye upon their will, that they cannot doe what they pleaſe, elſe to what purpoſe ſhould they take a Covenant: whence by the way I note, that that man w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> aſſumes an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute power where it is not given him, at the ſame time he both breaks his Covenant and uſurps that power.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If Magiſtrates have an abſolute power, as ſome would have had wholly in the King, why then the Kingdome lies at a very great uncertainty; it is upon one perhaps, that if the King or ſuperiour Magiſtrates be good, the Kingdome will be ſaved: but there are ten perhapſes, ten it may bees, for one that is contrary; that the King or Superiour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates are bad [eſpecially they knowing themſelves to have ſuch a power] upon which the deſtruction of the Kingdome lies; now there is no reaſon [I ſpeake for prevention of danger for future, whatſoever go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſhall be ſetled] that wee ſhould expoſe our ſelves to chance among ſuch rocks, eſpecially when wee know where they are, and how to avoid them, whereunto this is a ſtrong motive, to conſider, that though extreamity be the fitteſt ſeaſon for God to ſtep in and deliver; yet all other meanes muſt faile, otherwiſe it is to tempt God; for though God doth often deliver with the meanes, yet hee ſaveth not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114596:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:114596:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:114596:10"/> where lawfull means is not firſt uſed; why ſo, if there were no meanes of avoiding this abſolute power in Magiſtrates, we were free from our own deſtruction: but if we will obſtinately venter upon theſe rockes, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> upon a K. it may be juſt with God to ſplit us upon them; for the greateſt ſin of the <hi>Iſrael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> was their deſire to return into [after God had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed them] <hi>Aegyptian</hi> bondage, which at laſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their greateſt plague.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, If Magiſtrates have an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute power over the people, then that generall and undeniable maxime, <hi>ſalus populi ſuprema lex</hi> is but a vapour, it vaniſheth away: and ſo that which out of duty they are to prefer as the end of their truſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſubject to their unconſtant wills and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; For, the peoples ſafety [it being really conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the word of God, in that it confirmes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, every man to ſit under his owne Vine, as a bleſſing] that ſhould by all (if not ordinary) extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary meanes be endeavoured, is hereby made <hi>poſtrema lex,</hi> or rather no law at all, in that it is then dependant upon the wavering diſpoſition of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates; which if good, (as it is tenne for one to the contrary, in that they have more aboundance of temptations from ſuch an inherent power in them) yet where will appear the ſupremacy of the peoples ſafety, when it lies in the Magiſtrates power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nay, can we repute that people any other then ſlaves whoſe rights and liberties lie wrapt up in the will of uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Magiſtrates, whether in a King or others. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the rights and liberties of the people are much talked of: but when they come in queſtion of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, alaſſe, they gulp downe all the liberties, and therein the livelihoods of the people, into the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114596:10"/> honour, ſafety, and happineſſe of ſuch truſt-uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men, whoſe principles are to maintaine ſuch a power, which ſurely is not derivative, and therefore uſurpt; then which, nothing can tend more to enſlave a people, to whom, while ſo, to aſcribe any rights or liberties, is to mocke and deride them. For how can the people, rights and liberties be diſſolved into a Kings, or any other Magiſtrates will and power, and yet be theirs; therefore, when wee ſpeake of the peoples liberties, we doe (or at leaſt ſhould) meane ſomething peculiarly theirs; that for any man to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurp muſt needes induce the ſlavery, which is as much contrary to liberty, as light to darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now then it being clear, that it is uſurpatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates to aſſume an abſolute power; it follows by conſequence, that thoſe that doe ſo, are accompta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; for the very motion, life and ſoule, the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and the nouriſhment of ſuch a power in Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, is the peoples incapacity of oppoſing and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing that irruption upon their liberties by them: and to take away this power from the people, is to deprive them of their liberties; for how can thoſe be the poples (in that they are made incapable to maintaine them) liberties, when they are ſubject to the power of out-lawes; or wherefore have they a right or a title to them, if they cannot enjoy them; and how can they enjoy them, when they are at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers command; therefore ſeeing the people have a peculiar right and title unto liberties which cannot be enjoyed, unleſſe by their own power maintained, it is cleare, that the ſame law by which they may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavour the enjoyment of (which cannot be but in oppoſition to thoſe that would uſurpe) their rights, they may impartially puniſh ſuch uſurpers
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114596:11"/> anſwerable to their crimes; for the attempt of ſuch a power deſerves deveſtment, and much more the practiſing of it puniſhment. I ſhall proceed now to the objections.</p>
            <p>And the firſt is this; ſay ſome, have we not taken an oath of obedience to the late K. how then could it ſtand with our oath to diſobey him; to which I ſhal adde (becauſe both of a nature) that of another party, <hi>viz.</hi> Have not we covenanted to maintaine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and preſerve the honour, ſafety, and happines of the late Kings perſon; how then hath it conſiſted with our Covenant in taking away his life? To both which I ſhall anſwer but a little, becauſe I refer the Reader to be more fully and amply ſatisfied herein, by a Booke which I ſhall ſuddenly publiſh, entituled, <hi>Illumination to Sion. Colledge,</hi> by a moderate reply to their Letter delivered to the Generall, <hi>January</hi> 18. laſt.</p>
            <p>But to the firſt of the precedent objections, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that our oath of obedienee to ſuperiour Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates is, not was not abſolute, or without condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for then (as I ſaid before) to what purpoſe ſhould wee take an oath of him or them: and if our oath was abſolute, we ſwore our ſelves ſlaves, and therefore not a good oath, becauſe taken in ignor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: but how irrationall it is to think that we ſwore obedience univerſally, I need not demonſtrate; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it being cleare, that our oath was conditionally to yeeld obedience unto ſuperiour Magiſtrates in the execution of judgement and righteouſneſſe, which is the very end and cauſe of their authority and our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience: and which if they omit, we are as diſinga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from ſubjection to them as to a private perſon; becauſe that in this their duty the become as (and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114596:11"/> more incapable of power becauſe offenders, then] private perſons: And therefore like to this was the Covenant that <hi>David</hi> made with <hi>Iſrael</hi> when he was made King, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.3. Where it is ſaid, that all the Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> came to the King to <hi>Hebron,</hi> and King <hi>David</hi> made a Covenant with them before the Lord (a Covenant that he muſt keep if he would continue in his office) and (then) [after hee had Covenanted with them to make things ſure for the people] they anoynted <hi>David</hi> King over <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Now the very ſubſtance [which he accordingly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed] of his Covenant to them is manifeſt in the 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.14. So <hi>David</hi> reigned over all <hi>Iſrael</hi> and executed judgement and juſtice to all his people; there is a great deale of emphaſis in that particle <hi>ſo,</hi> So <hi>David</hi> reigned over all <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the execution of Judgement and Juſtice, [as that the very being of his authority depended upon the keeping of that his Covenant] to all his people, his people, how? Why [not that they were at his pleaſure, but he at theirs, as in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.3, 4. Where the people [not ſeeing it beſt for themſelves] told <hi>David</hi> he ſhould not goe forth in the Battell; to whom hee anſwered in the 4. <hi>Verſe.</hi> What ſeemeth you beſt, that will I doe; and <hi>David</hi> remained in the City, not for his owne ſafety but for the peoples, (in that they ſaw it) good] but they were his people while he performed his Covenant, after he had executed Judgement and Juſtice unto them: I have been long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in this anſwer then I thought, for ſatisfaction ſake.</p>
            <p>I ſhall very briefly anſwer that Objection of the other party in reference to the Covenant, that they ſay we made to preſerve the late Kings perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:114596:12"/> To this therefore I reply, that this clauſe in the Covenant is qualified with the ſubſequent end thereof, which [they willingly ſlip over] is, in the preſervation of our Religion and Liberties, the ſafety whereof is the end of our Covenant, and which we have ſworne to endeavour in oppoſition to all the enemies thereof; now if the Parliament ſhould, or as the late King did [notwithſtanding our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to preſerve them, which was no otherwiſe then they ſhould comply with us in endeavouring that end] turne enemies to what wee have Covenanted ſolely to endeavour, we are ingaged by our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to oppoſe them as enemies and impediments of attaining our end; but for more ample ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on herein, I refer the Reader to that prenomitated Book, and proceed to anſwer two or three objections more and then conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> Doth not God generally throughout the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture injoyne obedience to Magiſtrates as his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance? I anſwer, That though God doth frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Scripture injoyne obedience to Magiſtrates, yet it is not to all Magiſtrates, or to good Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in all caſes: Firſt, not to all Magiſtrates, for then Gods immediate command to <hi>Jehu,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9.6, 7, 8. to doe what hee did to his Maſter <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> the King, would directly contradict his owne Word if he ſhould injoyne us obedience to all, and command diſobedience in him; Againe, God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes not obedience to unlawfull Magiſtrates, ſuch as come not duely to their Office, and therefore the Apoſtle, <hi>Peter</hi> 1.2, 13. injoynes obedience to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, as being the ordinance of man; For ſaith he, <hi>Submit your ſelves unto every Ordinance of man
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114596:12"/> for the Lords ſake, whether it be unto the King as unto the ſuperiour:</hi> Superiour, what? not as the Monarch, none to contradict him, but as the ſuperiour Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man, or unto Governours as unto them that are ſent of him, for the puniſhment of evill doers, and for the praiſe of them that doe well; here is likewiſe a limitation to our ſubjection, it is not to obey in all caſes, but when they execute ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in the puniſhment of evill doers, and the praiſe of them that doe well; for this is their place, and if they doe not diſcharge this duty, they ceaſe to be Magiſtrates; and this I conceive to be the meaning of that place, becauſe it agrees with other Texts, 2. <hi>Samuel</hi> 5.3. Thus <hi>David</hi> was ordained, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.18. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.15. <hi>And Officers ſhalt thou make thee in all the Cities, which the Lord thy God giveth thee, &amp;c. And they ſhall judge the people with righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous judgement:</hi> Now then it is cleare that the Lord injoynes obedience to none but lawfull Magiſtrates and that in the juſt execution of their Office. I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeed now to the,</p>
            <p>Laſt Objection, and that is this, If Magiſtrates <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> offend, where is there any power to puniſh them; this objection hath in effect been cleared already, but I ſhall anſwer it now more formally; in caſe a Magiſtrate, though the ſuperiour, tranſgreſſe, there is a power above himſelfe (from whence he receives his Commiſſion) to which he is accountable, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as it were) but the peoples Factor; for God commands a people to execute Juſtice and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among themſelves, no man to wrong his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and many other civill Lawes to be obſerved, of which to eaſe themſelves and avoyde confuſion,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114596:13"/> they commit their truſt to Magiſtrates, and herein they promiſe particularly to obey them while they righteouſly diſcharge their Office; but now when to advance ſelfe, they begin to reſpect perſons in judgement, they become accountable to the people, or thoſe whom they ſhall chooſe to repreſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this judgement; and therefore wee often read that the avenger of blood appointed on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thereunto, was to ſlay the murtherer whoever he was, and when ever he met him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 35.21. <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.17. In other caſes likewiſe we finde that the Congregation it ſelfe was to give judgement; as when a man had accidentally (not voluntarily) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted murther, he was to remaine in the City of refuge till he did ſtand before the Congregation in Judgement; that is, before ſuch as they ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point thereunto, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 20.6. And therefore when GOD ſo often commands the people to execute Judgement and Juſtice without reſpect of perſons, it lyes upon their ſcore [though God will likewiſe reckon with thoſe whom they intruſt to doe it for them] if they omit it, <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.2. <hi>Whoſoever hee be of the Children of Iſrael or of the ſtrangers that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in Iſrael that giveth his Children unto Molech, he ſhall dye the death:</hi> Now here comes in the objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: What if a Ruler give his Children to <hi>Molech?</hi> Who ſhall kill him? Why the cloſe of the Verſe anſwereth it, <hi>The people of the Land ſhall ſtone him to death.</hi> But in the 4. Verſe. <hi>What if the people of the Land hide their eyes, and wink at that man, &amp;c.</hi> and kill him not? why in the 5. Verſe, <hi>Then</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>will I ſet my face againſt that man and againſt his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and will cut him off, &amp;c.</hi> But how ſad a thing is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114596:13"/> it when God ſhall finde none in a Land to make up the hedge, to worke righteouſneſſe, and thereby prevent God from taking the Sword himſelfe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute judgement; the Lord will power forth his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation upon them, and conſume them with the fire of his wrath, their owne wayes will he render upon their heads, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.30, 31.</p>
            <p>Now then the reſult of all will be this;</p>
            <p>That Kings if lawfull [under which title I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all Magiſtrates] are freely elected by the people, and accountable to them for their truſt:</p>
            <p>But the late KING was not freely elected by, neither would be accountable to the people:</p>
            <p>Therefore he was not a lawfull King, and his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſion was juſt.</p>
            <p>Againe,</p>
            <p>Gods Law injoynes the execution of Juſtice and Judgement:</p>
            <p>The Parliament in their late Tranſactions, have executed Juſtice and Judgement:</p>
            <p>Therefore they have obeyed Gods Law.</p>
            <p>For how abſurd is that opinion in ſome, that have complyed with the Parliament in puniſhing of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents, and yet they would leave the cauſe of them all unpuniſhed.</p>
            <p>For how unjuſt would that be in any Authority to puniſh the Servant for ill doing, and yet leave the Maſter [at whoſe command he was and whom hee obeyed therein] unpuniſhed; I could multiply examples of the like kinde, but to rationall men the premiſes will be ſufficient; but as for that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114596:14"/> way of Government by a King, it is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned in Scripture as a neceſſary way of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in that the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> 1.11. to the 18. ſo much dehorted the Prophet from it, and ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered the evill of it, and that it was a ſinne in the people ſo immoderately to deſire it; therefore it is left to a people to eſtabliſh what way of civill Government they ſee ſafeſt for themſelves, and in which, Judgement may run downe as Waters, and righteouſneſſe as a mighty River.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
